All right, good morning everyone.
Welcome to the event. This is the Atlas
stage. I'm Travis Fraser. I'm the stage
manager for Atlas. So, if there's
anything you need over this weekend,
please come to me. And I'd like to
introduce our first guest. It's Jen Ga
with Microsoft. So, come on up, Jen.
I'll start.
Hi, good morning. Uh, I'm Jen Hun from
Microsoft Research.
I'm very glad to uh have this
opportunity to present some of our
recent work. Um, I pick a few projects
around the topic called agenting
modeling. As I show you in the title of
the talk, right? This can see this.
Okay. Okay. Any modeling by
internalization aging harness. So before
I go into details, I want to give some
definition
uh regarding the three terminologies I
use in the title. Analytic modeling,
internalization
and agent harness
and agit modeling actually aim to
transfer large scale language models uh
into autonomous agent capability of
performing complex tasks by interacting
with the environment. We all know that
the portray the large scale language
model is mainly a talker. It seems that
the model knows everything but it's
really difficult if you ask about do
something for you. So agentic modeling
is the process where we want to turn
this talker to a doer
and uh the so-called Asian honey I think
everyone familiar with the uh uh with
the terminology. Okay. And usually it uh
because the larger language model cannot
do a lot of things. It's just a talker.
So in order to make the language model
to do some to perform some real world
task, you need to coupled with the large
language models sort of an an aging
harness. So when we talk about uh AI
agents, usually it's the combination of
the language model, probably multiple
language models and the aging harness.
In some sense, a harness is a bunch of
code. It can handle a lot of things that
the current language model cannot
handle. Well, internalization refers to
a process of distillering agentic
capabilities from the harness to
language model. What are these
capabilities? A great example is the
memory of contest management to use and
planning.
Uh typically this is achieved by mid
training and post training large
language models through supervised
learning or reinforce learning.
Okay.
Uh this figure shows the some key
components that are needed for engineic
modeling. There are three of them. Uh I
I I use different colors. Uh in the left
hand side, this part is the aging. For
example, we we assume that our lab is
not building a new large language model
because it is so uh resource intensive.
uh Microsoft has a dedicated team called
MAI and they are responsible for
building uh in-house large scale
language models such as MAI. Uh I think
they released uh a dozens of models um
recently helps Microsoft stocks. Okay.
Uh again we have deals contracts with
other companies such as open AI they
provide us and frontier models and we
have a store uh Asia foundry which can
host uh hundreds to thousands of uh open
source uh language models. Yeah. But the
focus of the lab actually is to develop
uh enabling technologies
to help develop uh the aging harness.
Aging harness can be viewed as a
hardcoded modules and the layers.
They're not models by themselves but
they are they're modules. Most of them
are hardcoded.
Uh these layers can do things that the
current language model cannot do. Well,
for example, the information layer
consists of the uh ma memory and the
context measurement and contains a lot
of tools and the scales for the language
model to call. And the execution layer
uh consists of a prompt builder
action par
deco composition modules uh and some
some arrow recovering mechanisms and
most importantly the feedback layer uh
which helps uh the system to collect all
the trajectories generated by the agents
and these trajectories can be used to
refine uh the underlying model the area
by post training. This actually is the
key of the uh agent modeling. Okay,
that's the first part. Second part is
the environment
and in some sense the environment
sometimes people call this reinforcement
learning environment or RE.
and where the AI agents can interact
with the external world to perform tasks
while generating trajectories.
And the last component is the yellow
one. It's the trainer. It's a model
trainer. Uh where the generated
trajectories are used to input larger
language models agentic capabilities by
post training and m training. Some of
the for example most important training
methods are reinforce learning and
expirations such as on policy distlation
uh reverse care divergence algorithms uh
actually here for the China the cost
efficiency uh is the key. So it's not
only that we require the model to be uh
served in a cost effective way.
More importantly we hope that the model
training uh is very sample efficient
meaning that probably we don't need a
lot of samples to train the model.
Uh putting together we witness a new
paradigm of AI modeling where harness is
like the training data to analytic
modeling just like the internet data to
model per training right as AI industry
and the community are building many many
uh AI agents and harness almost every
day then we can we actually witness an
emergence of a new data flywheel
uh where distating uh agent capabilities
from harness leads to AI models that are
more capable of doing things and which
these models can help us build even
better AI agents that can generate uh
more sophisticated uh uh trajectory data
and by solving uh more sophisticated
tasks. And again uh this process
continue as we advance both the harness
and the models. Okay. So many of the
ongoing uh AI research projects at the
MSR can be grouped uh into these three
categories as I outlined here. Uh and
for example the modeling technology as
in the green box. Yeah. to facilitate
harness engineering such as memory
management and test time learning and uh
the the the environment service as show
in the blue box and to host in parallel
many reinforced learning uh environments
where agents perform tasks that generate
trajectories
and uh actually this is the source of
the training data for agent modeling and
the yellow box the trainer
So
yeah in work for also I will present for
each group an ongoing research project
we recently released to the public or
we're about to release it. Uh on the
environment side I will present our
chart which is a opensource engine model
framework for research. Uh as for aging
harness, I will describe a new test time
learning framework called evolve lab
which allows large scale language models
to accumulate, reuse and involve
knowledge across a sequence of tasks.
And on the model trainer, I will present
GRO IO which is a new reinforcement
learning measure which I really hope can
provide an alternative to the dominating
ROI meas such as GP or PO because this
new method unlock the great diversity
and turns out to be a more cost
effective training method.
Okay.
Now this is the overall is a summary one
one one slide summary of the orchard
project and I I I believe the paper and
the code code and data will be released
sometime next week. Um we know that
despite the rapid progress in in in AI
aging the open research on agitic
modeling remains constrained by
infrastructure gaps early days when we
are doing this training oh the as long
as you have access to internet
there's a no lack of trend data you can
you can gra grab trend data from the web
but agent modeling different. You need
an environment
to run hundreds of thousands of uh
agents simultaneously so that they can
generate a lot of trajectory data and
then you can use this trajectory data to
train your model. So it's not there yet.
In the research community, people have
been focusing on uh infrastructure
mainly designed to improve the harness
itself but not the environment that can
host uh different agents different
agents to run uh in parallel. So to
narrow the gap we prevent uh present our
chart which is a open source ecosystem
for scalable agenting modeling. At the
core of the orchards is a sing coet
native environment service that provide
a reusable primitives of sandbox life
cycle environment.
It's called
ultra ev
uh ultra environment in some sense the
ultra environment is like an operating
system runtime for AI agents. It acts as
orchestration and the virtualization
layer that manage the container images
inside the sandbox that expose a clean
interface for the AI agents to run.
Intuitively speaking, what this does is
provide the environment. It's just like
the
uh organizer of this workshop organized
this conference, right? The operating
system in this contest is like the the
this building. Okay. It provides all the
electronicities facilities to us to host
a lot of workshops. If we view each
workshop as a agent, then the organizer
of this of this conference did a great
job to put each workshop in a particular
room. This is like a uh uh reinforce
learning environment many rece or or pod
in in in this context. And after all
these workshops
and the organizer will again collect all
the results of this workshop and share
the results with us in some sense the uh
or chart Evar is the organizer of this
uh the whole conference. Okay. Then in
order to demonstrate the effectiveness
of this environment we build three uh uh
a modeling recipes on top of that as a
demonstration. Okay. First is uh okra
eval or first is okra swing. This is
target to the software engineering
aging. what we did is we distill about
100,000
uh trajectories uh from from from from
the models and then and it's
interestingly we see that we got a very
good results 70 73% if you you know this
benchmark pretty well this we bench
verified and this result all already
supports a lot of open source models uh
regardless of the of the small size of
the model. Then we also uh take two
other examples
the the uh which is ultra uh GUI. GUI is
for navigation. The other is crow. Crawl
is for personal assistant.
Now the uh this is I I want to give a
quick update of of this project. It's
test time running learning within
involving libraries
and memory is important but typically we
view a memory uh as a storage of raw
experience
and but this experience is not learning
this exper
I collect a lot of experience previously
I I have no idea how to use this
experience to solve new tasks but human
learning is different. I never recall
all the details of my previous
experience. I only remember what
matters, right? The the the the the
failures I try to avoid, the new skills
I learned once and hopefully can apply
multiple times in the future. So this
algorithm uh is developed to simulate
the human learning.
Now the last project I want to uh
give an overview is uh is GRO I am. The
difference between this and the
traditional approach like the GPO is
that this in this uh reinforce learning
setting we define policy learning as
distribution matching rather than maxim
uh reward maximization. The key
difference is that now using this
algorithm we can sample uh trajectories
sample uh solutions proportional to the
reward they uh toward uh proportion to
the reward they got assigned. Okay.
Uh yeah I have to stop here. If you have
any questions feel free to to reach out
to me in offline manner. Thank you.
Thank you, Jang. Appreciate that.
All right. Next up, we have Sonia
Diddler with Nvidia.
I'll put it here.
>> All right. Can you hear me? I'm tall.
Um, yeah. Hi, I'm Sonia. I actually no
longer invidia. I just announced it
yesterday. Recently left. Um, but the
video has been really kind and actually
allowed me to take my slide deck with me
or at least quite a lot of the material.
So, I'll be talking about the Nvidia
work today. But, uh, today I'm a
civilian University of Toronto and I'll
let you speculate about my next steps.
Um, all right. So I'm not really going
to talk about you know agentic AI today
but I'm going to talk about world models
which is really something very exciting
to me really for the last six six years
but now this technology is is maturing
is is around the corner. All right. So,
um, you know, we've been working on
physical AI for quite a few years and
the world has been working on robots for
for for decades, right? Um, but if you
look at kind of this evolution of AI,
Chad GPT 2022 kind of the entire world
knew about AI. It was the first time
that really reached the masses. You
know, my mom knew about Chad GPT, right?
Um, right now we are in the era of
agentic AI. Everyone is using agents. I
don't need to explain what it is. I
cannot imagine my life actually without
using agents. And the next break point
that is coming perhaps you know in the
next decade maybe more depending on the
kind of robot we're going to looking for
is physical AI where all this
intelligence come to the edge comes to
the robots you know in many different
roles in many different industries.
All right. So at Invidia we were at
least my group was more focused on one
particular robot that was autonomous
driving robots. Today we're going to
kind of use that as an example. Um but
obviously there's many many robots
especially general robotics is kind of
the hot field that's upcoming and it's
the robot that kind of um
hearing a lot of echo uh supposed to do
many different tasks. Okay. So the
evolution of kind of the software to
deploy on smart robots for example a car
kind of went through different
generations. Um you know from very
simple AI very simple vision to more
hardcoding rules around how could I be
driving around to machine learning in
every single steps both in perception
but then also prediction and planning
and how I'm going to actually drive the
car. um to most recently end to end
systems where I'm just taking sensor
data and outcomes basically a planning
trajectory that drives the robot drives
the car um to perhaps you know the new
generation that's coming which is
leveraging this big foundation model
pre-trained on massive amount of data
that come with this you know vast
knowledge about how the world works
around all the corner cases that is so
hard to collect in the real world and
also know how to reason so people really
think kind of know this foundation model
is kind of gamecher to really kind of
that last mile to solve the corner case
u uh in robotics or in a navy as a first
complex example
all right today I'm not really going to
talk about so much about the software
that goes on the robot but about the
infrastructure
um particularly simulation right so if
you think about LLMs during development
people train a lot of different models
and you need to somehow evaluate um how
good they are which means sampling
something from the model, get some text,
you know, and have some some way of
evaluating how good it is. Sometime even
interacts with a human, right? If you
want to measure conversation. So
something like that in robotics actually
needs to be deployed um on a real robot
in closed loop, right? Meaning I have a
software, the brain of the robot, I
deploy it on a real robot. This robot
starts performing some tasks. Here I
have some video from Skilled AI that I
pulled from the internet. real robot
doing pick and place, you know, running
this policy which we'll develop in
neural environment and then you know the
human is kind of observing how good this
robot is doing right an alternative is
to actually have a robot do this in
entirely virtual world right on the
cloud. So it's a virtual robot in a
digital twin also doing pick and place
right and we can also evaluate how this
virtual robot is doing and that can also
give us a really good signal about which
which policy that we developed is
actually better right and we can also
train that way much more scalably. So if
you look at on the light left side
the development is kind of bounded by
deploying on the robot which runs with
physical time you know we cannot in the
real world we cannot run faster than the
physical time right so if you want to
scale and evaluate many many different
scenarios we need to buy many many
different robots
on the cloud on the other hand we're
bounded by compute time computers are
getting you know better and better we
can actually run faster than real time
and we just scale across GPUs, right,
instead of robots. So, it's a much much
much more scalable pipeline. So,
simulation is really kind of
foundational infrastructure for
robotics. I really don't think you can
develop robotics without really really
good simulation.
I skip this slide and um talking about
simulation, it has kind of gone through
different stages, right? So, you know,
traditionally this was done by graphics.
artists would carve out, you know,
create 3D assets, write behavior models,
write all the ray tracing equations and
then you would get out, you know, a
particular scenario.
It kind of worked, but at the same time
was so time consuming. If I wanted to
test my car at some streak in San
Francisco, you know, that goes one or
two months of actually artist time to
create that digital twin.
Then around 2020 a new technology came
along called nerf agotion splats that
completely changed the game and the the
game changer was that now you can go
from a recording from a real world
recording that you capture on a real
robot to a simulation environment with
some restrictions because it was all
done by reconstruction. So it's kind of
limited um with what you actually saw in
that recording but it was a game
changer. Suddenly the content problem
was solved. You could go from real world
capture to a simulation environment,
deploy a new version of your software
and make you know new closed loop
rollouts and actually test you know new
policies in this environment.
How did this work? You know it was all
reconstruction based. You have your
capture, you get your surface
reconstruction for collision checking
and then unifor splat this kind of
little appearance blobs in space that
tell you how to render different
viewpoints.
Complete game changer. At Nvidia, we
were doing two million simulations per
day testing autonomous driving software.
All right. So, is that enough or what's
coming next? Like I said, there was a
lot of limitations of how you
reconstruct the environment, what kind
of environment you can actually handle.
Plus, at the same time, it's only
bounded by what you have recorded and we
talked about the robotics is going to
hit the long tail, which is stuff that
you it's so hard to see and you actually
need to test and train in those
environments. So, it's all about
imagining those hard cases as well. And
this is where you know world models or
generative world models come in right
this is AI purely trained on data it's
completely datadriven you know there's
no more human in human crafting content
um so the limit is the data and we have
learning LLMs that's basically you know
the way to go and suddenly you can
hallucinate new scenarios you can write
you know whatever new hard edge case you
you you imagine and uh very kind of hard
dynamic scenarios,
lots of progress on this front, right?
Especially in the last year. Uh, now we
can generate, you know, really crazy
hard scenarios.
Um, what's kind of like hard weather and
no one got hurt in that video. It was
completely generated accident. Just
really kind of those cases where you
want to test the software.
Here we can even change the viewpoint
which is similar to basically changing
embodiment you know going from you know
lower car sports car to a truck. Super
important. So you can actually test
across different vehicles.
And the last really important thing
that's very easy to do with generative
models but a little harder with a
reconstruction tag uh is editing. You
know just text from and suddenly you can
edit scenario in different ways.
All right. There's a specific um um
architecture that I have in mind when I
talk about world models today and it's
interactive. So it's not just I'm
getting text, I'm getting out a video,
five seconds of video. Uh it there's a
there's a user or a robotic software in
the loop here. My favorite human at was
actually our first user. As soon as we
developed the model went to his office
and he was the one trying it with a real
steering wheel. So in this case it was a
user driving and every single frame that
you saw was completely generated by the
world model and that's what I mean by
world model in this presentation and uh
that's by being interactive. You know
there's a robot or a human in the loop
and that model that uh uh we develop was
called omnidreams uh and the bonus is
that it runs real time. Does simulation
need to run real time? Not necessarily.
It just needs to have really high
throughput, but real time is a great
bonus.
All right, so I'll just go do a quick
glance of how we actually develop this
today. Obviously, in the future, this is
going to be a lot maybe simplified and
so on. But right now, everyone started
with a base model. This is a pre-trained
video generation model. Um, typically
based on diffusion. So, you have a few,
you know, like a noisy frames and you
den noiseise them into, you know, a few
second of video. This is what I mean by
birectional uh attention model.
Now we typically do domain post
training. This was pre-trained typically
you know on vast amount of uh publicly
available internet data. Now you need to
go to a specific robotic domain for
example AV and you need to posturing
such suddenly I can start generating
stuff that happens on the road right and
not just stuff that happens on the road
stuff that c is captured by a robot
which is typically more than just one
single camera it can be many different
cameras
then we need to train this architecture
right we said we need to make it
interactive so we actually change to
have this causal architecture right so I
need to generate frame by frame it's
like not short snippets of video at a
time with action in the loop. We need to
make it efficient. Typically in this
diffusion models you do many steps of
distillation which makes it slow but you
need to distill it into just a few step
of the distillation. So it can actually
be much faster and then you do all the
tricks in the book to actually have a
real-time implementation and this is
flash dreams we uh released it and you
can plug it on different architectures
of world models and then the world model
comes out. So here you have someone
driving. On the right side is a steering
wheel that's being operated. Every
single frame here is not the real world
is completely generated by the world
model.
And here we have very simple physics.
It's just physics on the ground. So we
make sure that the car stays always on
the ground, goes over speed bumps. Um
but you can actually go through a
restaurant no problem. So we didn't have
collision checking on on more complex
comp complex part of the scene than the
road.
All right. Um I wanted to show this
because I think it's really showing the
trajectory of where this is going. Um
March 2025
we were generating 5-second clips typic
five minutes or so. 5 seconds 5 minutes
of GPU time. Okay. It was clearly not
practical. on the right side March 2026
this was fast forward one year real time
interactive
okay so this is how fast this technology
is uh evolving this is why I mean it's
around the corner
um at CVPR which was basically two
months later this was June we even made
it work on RTX uh 5090 which is
basically a consumer grade GPU which is
awesome it's literally a game engine
that you can have in a backpack
um just some examples results.
Everything here you see is completely
generated and you know it's just giving
it a text from or a first frame and you
get a desired scene which much more
complex. There's no way that this can be
done by graphics engine. It's just too
much or too too many different phenomena
going on and it's very hard for the
construction tech to actually generate
this as well. So,
and this is basically showing what you
need to do in the end, which is generate
multiple different sensors that you have
on the robot.
And this is pretty cool uh because here
we're actually editing the same
environments. We can change the weather,
the lighting conditions, and that little
green trajectory that you see, that's
actually the robots policy driving in
this world. I was actually super excited
about this result because we plugged it
in in the production policy and was
driving in this world. It's it's
confusing this simulated world with the
real world which is basically means that
you're that your quality bar is at the
level that you actually need.
Yeah. And I asked my guys to generate
some some cool examples. And this is
basically just saying that you still
capture that you know internet
knowledge. So even though Invidia has
never hap captured an elephant on the
road, we can actually generate it which
is proving the point on that long tail.
Yeah. And then maybe just kind of end
here with uh the interactive demo. Um
just so that you see it actually runs
real time. On the left side is a person
really driving it. Every single frame is
generated. On the right side you see
that wheel rotating. That's actually the
robotic software operating that wheel
and driving in this like three camera uh
world model.
So thank you very much. I'll stop here.
[applause]
All right. Thank you Sonia. I appreciate
that. Next up we have Gian Batista
Parisand Doyo or GB with OpenAI.
>> [applause]
>> There you go.
Okay. In the meantime,
uh there's this saying that there's
nothing more stale than yesterday's
newspaper. Well, these slides are five
years old. Every single one is from four
to five years old. So, um
well, if we get the slides,
okay, so why are these slides old? Um
I'm basically going to show you the some
of the earliest presentations that we
had internally at OpenAI when we started
work on reasoning. So this is talking
not it's not about the future. Um the
slides are also really ugly because
these were never meant to be presented
in any occasion like this one. So these
are just slides for our teams from a
long time ago. So think about it as more
as a whatever time traveling and seeing
what was like to work on reasoning a
while ago. Okay. So, first what is
reasoning? Um, again, these are the the
old slides. So, maybe one way to think
about it is to say there's a big space
of problems of all kinds of subjects.
And then you could think of this
colorful wheel as all of the different
things you could be thinking about. Uh,
so there's AI and math and physics and
biology. Um, and then let's say the the
central radial axis is difficulty. So,
as you move the angle, you change the
subject. as you move away from the
center, you change the difficulty. And
so the main thing we were having at the
time is that we were pre-training all of
these models like GPT um two and three
and four and then the circle of problems
they could solve would expand from the
middle and they would kind of cover all
of the subjects uh a little bit and
solve slightly harder and harder
problems as we went. Um then the main
issue is when were we going to solve the
really hard problems and then if you
think about some of the human experts in
different subjects for example uh Andrea
Wilds who solved for mass theorem well
this guy thought about this problem for
for seven years but it's not like he
could solve everything uh at the same
time that took seven years to solve he
could solve one problem that took seven
years and most of the hard problems are
like that and so in some way there was
something about this process of just
pre-training models to be better at
general knowledge that seemed unlikely
to eventually expand the circle all the
way to cover all the hardest problems.
So what do we do as humans? We we think
we reason. So can we give models the
same capabilities?
Okay. So now we're going to do something
uh a little fancy. We're going to move
this wheel in 3D. So we're going to tilt
it this way. So pay attention because
it's only going to happen once. Um okay.
So now it's on the side and we're going
to move it to the side of the screen.
And now we can add the third axis which
didn't exist before which is uh time. So
thinking time. And then the question
becomes how do we expand these cylinders
that don't really cover anything else
given more time. Uh maybe it might look
a bit ridiculous today but there was a
time where you would give a model more
time to think and it would give you the
exact same answer because after a few
milliseconds you would get the answer
and it would know uh it would not not
know what to do with the extra time. And
so so thinking was this idea of well can
we can we expand this cone over time um
and not all at once again you have to
pick one uh little thing to focus on and
then discover that and so uh there were
lots of practical problems I'm not going
to talk about almost any of them um but
the thing to also think about is well
how long is this reasoning because again
Andrew Wild thought about this for seven
years and so in terms of um our models
well at the time they only had a context
of a few thousand tokens maybe 8,000
tokens and then what can you do with
8,000 tokens? Well, at most a few
seconds of reasoning and so there were
lots of interesting questions of you
know even if we get to them to reason
that how is this going to happen? Okay,
now um the other issue was we didn't
know what reasoning would use as a
substrate. There were lots of different
ways you could spend test time compute,
right? You could do you can have a
recurring network and do lots of steps
internally. Um what turns out the text
works really well and so um again these
are some very old slides. This is a
actually was of my first project when I
joined OpenAI and I'm just going to show
you um like a like a little exploration
of what models could do but just asking
them to think when they were not ever
trained to think. Um and this is one of
the pieces that gave us confidence to
scale things up. And so okay again these
are the old slides. Um the pitch was
what if we just asked them all to think
about it. Um, and so I had a bunch of
examples. We're going to go through
them. Again, they're very silly for
today's standards, but it's good to see
how far we went in such a short amount
of time and where we used to be at the
time. So, uh, at the time, you could ask
GPT3
uh, a simple math problem. There are 29
bags of potatoes and then um, 17 more
and there's plenty of bags and the model
would say that there's 46 kilos of
potatoes which obviously completely
wrong. And so one of the first
exploration was to just add let's think
about it before getting the answer. Then
the thing you would get is you wouldn't
get an answer right away. The model
would start to output some extra text.
But then eventually you would get the
right answer. And of course not all the
time, but at least sometimes compared to
never. Okay. So then we uh kept going.
Um a bunch of questions. I have a
clarinet, a piano, a dog. How many
musical instruments do I have? Malo said
one. Um that's of course wrong. Uh
clarinet and pianos are both
instruments. You would break it down. to
think about it step by step and then you
would get you know dog is a music it's
not a musical instrument a clarinet is a
musical instrument but a piano is not so
it's still one um and so then you try to
think okay well if this only thought a
little longer and so you add well also
break it down step by step and then say
well you know first we have a dog is not
a musical instrument and then via piano
is musical instrument um a client is um
and so then you get the right answer um
here's one more example there's a chair
amp and oven lots of sub lots of things
and then the model would say 20 and the
answer is 14. Uh back in the days you
could check what was the probability of
getting the answer 14 out of the model
and the answer the probability was uh
2%. So basically almost never. Um then
again you add let's think about it break
it down step by step and then you get
this long list when the model counts one
by one and somehow you get a better
answer. Okay so this intuition is seems
good. And how do we make it
quantitative? And this was one of the
first plots about what happens if we get
this model to think for longer. And so
these are the last two plots I have to
show you. This is just if you do this
trick of asking the model, well, think
step by step and then think step by
step, break it down and um keep adding
sentences to say, look, I really want
you to do all the work and show all your
work and make sure there are no
mistakes. Um and so we went from this
model that could barely solve problems
to by just adding things um get to
models that could solve more and more
problems by by thinking longer. And so
the last plot I want to add is this one
which should have gone with the other
one. Um and this is the average length
of the solutions generated by the model
when you asked to solve a problem. And
so again at the beginning you would get
almost nothing if you just asked to
solve and then as you kept adding
instruction and you know you had to use
this trick of saying first comma so the
model wouldn't again just try to answer
and get into this mindset of okay it's
going to be a long list of things I need
to do. So you know first this something
something then there must be a second
and a third and so let's try to output a
lot of text and so as the amount of text
the model was outputting was increasing
then the accuracy of the model was going
up. Um yeah and so since then um lots of
other people worked on this we did a big
project and then uh lots of other
components we can't talk about yet but
um yeah very humble beginnings uh one of
many and I thought it was interesting
maybe for you guys to see this in uh in
the midst of this talks about the future
all right that's all thank All
right, thank you GB. All right, next up
we have Adit Grover with Inception Labs.
Welcome up.
All right. Um, hello everyone. Uh, my
name is Adita. Uh, I'm one of the
co-founders and the CTO at Inception.
And today what I'm going to talk about
is actually going to take a lot of
elements from what we just heard in the
previous talks into defining what I
believe will be the new foundation for
generative AI. something that's
extremely fast and efficient and builds
on ideas from diffusion.
So, uh to
to take
Okay, maybe it's
so uh to take a trip down um memory
lane. Um, I think there have been a few
fundamental advances that have defined
uh what AI looks today and what I
believe AI is going to look like in the
future. And at the heart of all of these
advances is the idea that
parallelization is a fundamental concept
for computer science, fundamental
concept for AI and fundamental belief
that will also guide towards the future.
So if you think about the late 90s uh
the idea that we finally had hardware
which could execute a very simple but
basic operation called matrix
multiplication in parallel was turned
out to be the defining moment for what
we see in today's generative AI world.
uh a few years later we realized that
there's also something that could be
done in terms of architectures when we
had the transformer itself as the
fundamental neural architecture which
could be used to train AI models in
parallel and this was how from the world
of RNNs and LSTMs which were
fundamentally bottlenecked by how much
they could learn with every dollar of
compute spent we went into a new era
where we could train massive language
age models using the transformer
architecture.
Within all of this um we also have
started thinking about how this ideas
could then also be applied on the
algorithm side and that's where there
were fundamental advances in vision that
continue to be the state-of-the-art
today. So we have diffusion which
replaced what was at that time the
dominant paradigm based on GANs to
become the dominant way in which we
generate images and videos extremely
efficiently and with very high fidelity.
Now this was something which um works
extremely well even today but so far
most of the state-of-the-art
demonstrations of diffusion have been
limited to images but there has been a
recent fave of work now taking in the
same ideas and applying it to the field
of text. Now why is text hard? So uh to
understand why text is very different
from images, it simply boils down to the
fact that the notion of diffusion was
invented for continuous modalities. So
if you think about modalities such as
images, there's a very natural notion of
what it means to add noise and then a
good mathematical theory to what it
means to do a principal denoising of it.
Text on the other hand happens to be
discrete which makes it fundamentally
very hard to think about what are good
notions of noising and dnoising which
can be trained at scale.
So at inception what we've been doing is
trying to build a new generation of
language models which apply this idea to
long range uh text sequences. And how it
basically works is that instead of
generating tokens sequentially one token
at a time which is what practically all
language models of today do that's the
auto reggressive paradigm that you see
at the bottom. What we are now doing is
we are coming up with a way in which you
can den noiseise text. So you could
start with something that's extremely
gibberish and then pass it through a
neural network. This can be any
architecture. we use transformers
uh and through this transformer neural
network, you're now training it to fix
the noise in its input. So that's how
you can then find structure within text
and generate something extremely
coherent in much shorter amount of time
because now you're trying to predict all
the D noiseis tokens in parallel.
So this is tracing down the history of
text diffusion. Um so in 2019 is when uh
denoising diffusion started taking off
for images. So this was the time when
companies like midjourney um as well as
from other labs including Google openai
were coming up with uh very large scale
demonstrations of how diffusion can uh
generate extremely high quality images.
uh it took many years and work of the
entire research community to come up
with ideas which eventually led us to
the point where there was a breakthrough
from one of my co-founders lab where we
were able to then design a diffusion
model for text that achieved parity with
GPT2.
Now, of course, in 2024, uh, GPD2 was no
longer the bar for success in language
and that's when we decided to form this
company called Inception and really take
this idea at scale. A few months later,
uh we launched Mercury, which is the
first commercial scale diffusion
language model and uh it was able to
generate text uh for at very good scales
and do a lot of good tasks including
code editing, code generation, uh
mathematical problem solving, common
sense at scale and extremely fast. And
this of course also caught the attention
of a lot of notable folks in the field
uh both in academia and industry.
Very quickly a few months later many
different labs from Google to Nvidia to
Alibaba followed up with their own
efforts in building the fusion LMS. And
earlier this year we launched the second
iteration of our model Mercury 2 which
now also had capabilities to do
reasoning.
And unlike other LLMs, uh, diffusion
reasoning looks very different from how
uh, it works for auto reggressive LLMs.
And the best way to illustrate that is
through this chart. So this is a chart
from artificial analysis uh, which is
comparing Mercury with uh, the
state-of-the-art LLMs for the speed
optimized regime from different labs. So
on the x-axis you see the speed that's
measured by tokens per second. So higher
is better. And on the y-axis you're
looking at some kind of quality index.
In this case it's the one that's defined
by artificial analysis across a wide
range of agentic benchmarks.
And what you see here is that mercury
gets you similar quality as
um as as you would see for models of
similar uh size. So if you think about
your claude haikus, you think about the
GPD 5 minis. So these are all the speed
optimized models from Frontier Labs. And
it gets you similar quality while being
much much faster. And that's because
it's denoising tokens in parallel. It's
breaking away from the paradigm of
generating tokens sequentially.
So uh this has now been commercialized
as well. So we provide a drop-in
replacement for existing language models
and uh there's a lot of different
applications that are being built on top
of these models. So a lot of them are
ones where speed is extremely critical
uh along with also concerns of cost and
all of this has to be done at a desired
level of quality. So some of the domains
where we are seeing a lot of success is
in voice and coding and search. Just to
show you a few case studies of how this
has come to the real world. So in for
voice and support agents what you can
see is that what you really care about
is not just intelligence alone you care
about intelligence as well as the time
for response. So in particular the time
to first token is extremely important
for any kind of customer support voice
kind of applications
and for these kinds of applications if
you look at these charts what it's
really showing is that Mercury defines a
different kind of frontier where it gets
you extremely good intelligence at a
very small time to first token. In fact,
uh, compared to even non-reasoning
models such as GPD 4.1, which is in
production at most of the voice
companies, Mercury 2 can do reasoning
and still be faster than a GPT model. So
that's what speed buys you where you can
actually deploy reasoning models at the
speed uh or even better than
non-reasoning models. So extremely good
quality at a fraction of the speed.
Now um one thing also notable in this is
all of our deployments are on Nvidia
hardware. So this is coming purely
because of the fact that we have trained
these models using diffusion and we're
generating tokens in parallel. So any of
these complimentary advantages such as
those that could arise from modern
hardware like Cerebras and Grock could
pair up potentially very well with
having a diffusion model for text on top
of it.
Um this is another case study for
search. In this case uh you not only
care about speed, you also care about
cost. So these two plots are showing how
accuracy varies with each of these
factors. And again you see a similar
kind of trend where the models that you
can actually deploy in production should
have a good combination of all three and
mercury strikes a really good balance in
this space as well.
uh coding is another space of course um
I can't imagine my life now without
using coding agents and what you see
with coding agents is again that you
might have a primary agent that's
extremely verbose uh or might use a lot
of tokens uh but that's not always what
you need in order to drive down the
token economics towards something that's
sustainable so companies like augment
code are using mercury in conjunction
with some of the more heavyweight models
like opus to get a very good balance
reduce latency as well as cost zero
and um I I would end with this slide
where if you think about the frontier of
intelligence uh we have reached a point
where we have extremely good
intelligence for a lot of applications
but now what's really important is as we
build value for everyone around us is to
think about the new currency of
intelligence per watt and the fusion
LLMs seem like a really good bet to
redefining that frontier. Thank you.
>> All right, thank you Adita. Next up we
have a a workshop from Daytona and it's
going to be an hour session and after
that's going to be lunch. So welcome up
Daytona.
All right.
All right. You want to see if you can
plug in right here. So, this is this is
the main one.
You want to go
else?
running. I think he's probably
giving me a signal here.
Go straight into the HDMI.
Can you choose the mirror?
That's it.
Just have a turn.
remember
my
this morning.
>> See mine works. Do you want to Is it
possible to transfer
I know that's working,
>> but his isn't working.
should be shown here. I don't know why.
Your application
We would see it here.
That will go
understand
Sorry about that. We're having some
technical difficulties.
So it's
He's
ready for that.
Yeah. Can we try to look at
Let me plug my computer in just to
>> This is very odd.
Oh yeah.
overact.
Serious.
I Obviously,
I don't know why.
I guess
you're all good.
I'm sure
I just don't know how to like think
about it.
I want
>> Yeah. One second.
I can write the paper on it.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, cool.
>> Like
All right, everyone. We've got it solved
and Daytona is going to present their
workshop. Sorry about the technical
difficulties. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Um, sorry about that. Yeah,
thank you to everyone who stayed um for
being patient and stuff. Okay,
cool.
Okay. All right. So,
[clears throat] hey everyone. I'm
Muhammad. I'm a developer relations
engineer at Daytona. Um at Daytona, for
those of you who don't know, we build
infrastructure for running agents and
their workloads. Um so we basically
provide computers you can create through
an API and compose uh you know choose
their operating system, choose however
many CPUs, how much RAM, uh disk, etc.
And the two primary use cases um why
people use this are for running agents
in the background or on the cloud and
also um for reinforcement learning. Um
and so like to kind of understand that
is like when you train an agent, the
model learns by doing the task. Um and
coding agents or computer use agents,
they need a compute environment to
perform those tasks. And so um our
infrastructure happens to be pretty well
suited um for that use case. And um
yeah, the uh the talk or the workshop is
kind of about how we came to this point
like how exactly we went from you know
chat bots to today's agents. Um, you
know, a few years ago,
uh, the state of the art was like an LLM
that you, um, sort of treated as like a
question and answer assistant. It would
sometimes be helpful. Um, but I couldn't
actually do anything, but now they they
can they can act. And so,
um, yeah, I that's going to be the
presentation essentially. Um, so the
first half I'm going to be kind of going
over the history, how we got to the
current point. And the second half my
colleague Lou is going to be going over
kind of like where Daytona fits into
this and some of the more modern
techniques um that uh our infrastructure
shines in.
Um, cool. So I think like um you know
everyone is probably somewhat familiar
with this like the classic uh you know
terminal agent. Um this is an example of
Kimmy K3.
Um
you know you give it a prompt to fix a
bug you know uh implement a feature and
it starts running a bunch of commands
writing files etc. Um now I want you to
consider let me see if I can go to the
next slide.
This is the same model um given the same
you know tools um all LLS SQL or not the
same model same harness same tools uh
but it's GPT2 so this is a model from
seven years ago and so when you send the
same prompt um it just it just breaks it
doesn't know what to do and um yeah
that's kind of the main point is
understanding you know how the
difference between these two slides um
and kind of the I guess the short answer
is reinforcement learning. Um
but what's interesting is like there was
sort of two uh developments happening at
the same time. One is um you know people
kind of uh reinforcement learning is not
a new thing. It's been
um been a thing for multiple decades.
Really just what changes kind of the the
model behind it and um what get what
gets rewarded. And so this is sort of a
timeline of um what I'll be talking
about.
And it's helpful to also understand like
um how an LLM works
and to kind of get a uh to get a better
understanding later on when we talk
about like what gets rewarded, how does
you know a model actually learn, what
does learning really mean? Um, and so
like this is kind of the the most basic
um example of an LLM. So you have like
you know it's writing a sentence and the
next token is calculated by sampling
from a probability distribution. And so
like at each step you know you have um
a certain amount of tokens to choose
from. Some are more likely, some are
less likely. Um sometimes the least
likely one that gets picked. Um
and so yeah, I think this architecture
is not um probably super new to most
people, but um yeah, that's that's sort
of the motivation behind uh or the
background behind like what what
pre-training is. Um so you want to make
the model output
u the whatever you're training it on. So
if you're training it to be a helpful
assistant or um maybe it's just like
completing a Wikipedia page entry,
you kind of let the model, you know,
output what it thinks is the most likely
next token and then grade it based on
the actual ground truth. Um so this is
sort of a example of um see sort of a
like a zooming in on how it works. So
you have at the top is the ground truth
of what the model is being graded on and
then the bottom is each token that I
outputed and so you can kind of go
through each step. So like right now
we'll just look at this token at the end
crew. Um
we see that like
the so when the model was
sorry when the model was um you know
prior to this step where its weights got
updated
um the probability at the time was
um 61% and then you know when the loss
gets calculated which the loss is just
um
the negative log probability that step
gets applied to its weights and then all
the kind of previous tokens uh the
weights get updated to be uh to match
the ground truth more often. Um so you
can kind of go you know you can see each
one. It's a little bit cluttered slide.
Hopefully something you guys can read it
but yeah you can see exactly how the
weights and uh the probabilities got
updated.
Um,
and so you know after you kind of had
like models that just completed a
sentence and a pattern that kind of
emerged from that is you could show it a
um pattern where let's say you have like
for example this is a sort of a a toy
pattern but um I guess more realistic
example would be
if you had a you know a list of Python
functions and then you wanted it to fill
in like the fourth one, then it would
know somehow that uh it would learn from
the three patterns that you showed it in
the input and then like um pretty
accurately predict what the fourth one
would look like based on that pattern
that you showed it. Um and that's all
you know just in the prompts. You don't
that didn't require any like um you know
teaching the model to do that. It just
saw the pattern and and kind of learned.
Um
and so like the point is like nobody
really this is kind of a emergent
property that fell out like no one um
kind of like built that pattern into the
weights. It just fell out of next word
prediction.
And we noticed that like if you take
that same concept and you just apply it
to a larger model, it gets a lot better
at um
uh following those patterns.
And
there was this kind of a few years ago
this paper about thinking step by step.
And um basically you can kind of see and
some some of you might remember how when
you would prompt like GPT and you
explicitly told it to kind of uh you
know think more systematically, think
more carefully, it got the right answer,
um it would it would be able to you know
kind of quoteunquote reason about the
problem and arrive at the right answer
more often uh than not.
And um
so the the way that I was kind of
showing up until this point mostly just
models that completed the sentence,
whatever you uh gave it as input. Um but
I think most people remember models
behaving as assistants. But in order for
it to get to that point, it kind of had
to learn the pattern of being an
assistant. U and so the way that that
happened was just you show it a bunch of
question and answer samples and it
learns that pattern. Um it kind of
understands okay um depending on the
question you want to be like a helpful
assistant to the user. And so
um that was another kind of like major
shift. And yeah, this is, you know, an
example of
uh a query you might ask um one of those
assistant models like the answer would
be something that that is hopefully
helpful.
I don't know if we'll be able to
Yeah, this is kind of the the same
concept earlier where
you kind of like update the weights so
that the model learns how to behave more
like an assistant more often.
Sorry.
Um, yeah, I think these slides are kind
of repeating that concept more or less.
Um
and so the the I guess some limitation
was reached uh that's kind of like
fundamentally limited in that like you
can teach it to imitate patterns but um
really like if you
let's say you had a data set from a math
textbook and all you did was
uh kind of like reward it based on
whatever tokens
would lead to um would lead to the final
answer.
That's
in a way like prescribing how the model
should behave to get to the answer. And
um this will sort of make sense later
on. It's limited in that we don't know
exactly like I guess what the best way
is to arrive at that answer inherently.
And so um what kind what kind of
motivates like reinforcement learning is
that all you do is you know reward the
final answer and then hopefully
uh which um it did turn out to be true.
The model would um kind of the reasoning
from the model would emerge from that
point as opposed to you know having um
humans kind of like tell it how to
reason.
Um and yeah this kind of a basic diagram
of reinforcement line every year agent
it acts on an environment and then
receives a reward.
Um and
so one thing before even getting to um
reasoning I think
uh there was this like
concept of
um human feedback
uh you know which which response would
you prefer to hear when you uh when when
you receive that response. Um, you might
remember using GPT and like giving two
different responses. Not sure if they
still do this, but um, yeah, you kind of
choose what you prefer.
And then based on that, a reward model
gets trained that kind of makes the
underlying LLM more
aligned to whatever humans prefer.
Um, and so
this is getting a little bit I think
I'll probably have to skip some of these
slides for the sake of time, but um,
this is the objective that, uh,
is optimized when doing a reinforcement
learning with human feedback.
And so, yeah, sort of a an example of
what I've been talking about.
Let's get these.
And so yeah, going back to what I was
saying earlier, you know, if if we know
that reasoning helps um then why
why do we try to teach it to imitate a
written solution? Um you know why not
just reward it based on the finalizer
and then see kind of what comes out of
that. So
that's [clears throat] where
reinforcement learning with verifiable
words came uh or kind of showed that
um a model can without even being told
how to arrive at the final answer
necessarily
if it just gets rewarded based on its
final answer um it'll learn to reason
better and that'll transfer to other
problems.
And so this is kind of a fast forwarded
um
fast forwarded output of deepse R1. And
so like
instead of you know going back and
seeing did it reason correctly? Did
every token up until the final answer
um match what was in my data set? All we
do is check the final answer.
Um
and so
uh one thing that sort of one problem
that emerges from that is if you have a
you know really long reasoning chain and
it does get the final answer or it gets
it incorrect you know how do you know
which which tokens in that trajectory
like earn that reward? Um maybe some
maybe the model was going down a path
that was reasonable and you know later
on let's say like a few thousand tokens
in it took a bad path. Uh maybe you
don't want to you know penalize the
quoteunquote good tokens. Um
and like
the I guess the answer to that at the
time was having a critic model. um which
kind of like guesses like okay is this
token that was predicted um
you know better than expected as in
was it already very likely to um you
know output this token because in that
case it probably doesn't deserve to be
rewarded as highly as other unlikely
tokens. Um hopefully that makes a little
bit sense but um that sort of required
like you know training in tandem uh
another model.
Um but this other
uh the solution to that at the time that
kind of like changed um changed things
and made made things a lot more
efficient than having to you know train
another model is um this other policy
optimization group relative policy
optimization. Um
so instead of like
doing one sample and then grading every
token in that trajectory, you sample a
group and then you sort of use
uh you sort of use the
having multiple rollouts as a proxy to
like uh which rewards are more deserving
of credit. So
um as an example,
let's say you have uh on one task four
rollouts or four attempts at that task
and like most of them pass uh but one of
them fail. So that means like the one
that failed was pretty unexpected or
like unlikely. And so we really really
want to make sure those tokens are um
penalized harder than the other ones are
rewarded because it's already pretty
likely to get the correct answer. And if
we don't really take care of this like
relative um
reward, if we reward everything equally
um then you can imagine like
the model converge towards one kind of
way of doing things.
Um so that's kind of the motivation
behind like why we want to assign credit
um particularly
um and this is a yeah so this is sort of
a
example of
what I showed in the previous slide. So
like we have four
trajectories here. One of them received
here. There you go. You know, two of
them received the low reward to receive
the high reward. And I'll just go
quickly over like
what it might look like. Um so you know,
you calculate the advantage based on the
mean reward and then use that to
calculate the loss. And then that sort
of um updates all the weights.
Um and yeah,
and so like
[clears throat] we still haven't really
answered like how how did we get to the
point where models could actually do
things, right? Um
you know to for a model to write code
ideally it could test that code that way
like you know at least you know that it
failed before you know pasting that into
your editor. And so
this is a this is kind of where the
concept of tool calling came where a
model can output certain tokens and
those will get parsed as um kind of a
almost like a function execution
essentially you look at the I think I
have an example on the next slide
actually that'll just make things a
little bit clearer.
No, never mind. So yeah, um essentially
you
look at
special tokens that the model outputs
for
um depending on how you might want to
train it,
you teach it to output tool calls on a
certain format and then um it learns to
you sort of like reward it to output in
the format and then reward it to use
that more often when solving any
problems it might be uh it might be
given.
And then it learns to, you know, when it
uh thinks it needs to call a tool, it
outputs those tokens, wraps whatever it
needs to run. So in this case, um this
model I'm using wanted to run this
command. And so there's a parser not
shown here that waits for an output that
looks like that from a model um
uh that's wrapped around
special um special tokens.
And when it sees that, yeah, kind of
executes that in an environment.
Um, but one tool call isn't really an
agent. An agent is, you know, like we
know them today. They keep on acting
until uh and observing until the task is
done or until it, you know, thinks it's
done.
And um
this is sort of like
uh sort of the evolution that we well
it's a little bit outdated
not not super outdated but um yeah you
guys probably remember at first it was
like you know GitHub co-pilot and then
the agent actually like lived in your
editor and now like we use terminal
agents um or some people might still use
editors or other UIs but yeah and so
like the point is that the the
environment um that we think of like
when we think of reinforcement learning
became a computer because you know these
agents coding agents they need to call
tools that you know file editing tool
code execution tool has to be executed
in some compute environment and so like
training an agent now
you know you have to deal this was the
case previously but now it's like at a
larger scale you sort of like have to
deal a lot with cloud
infrastructure and handling that. Um
that's sort of um like I said earlier,
yeah, one of the reasons why um people
use Daytona for reinforce reinforcement
learning. Um, and actually to make that
more concrete, my teammate at is
going to come up and kind of show you
guys some uh go over how our
infrastructure fits in, what role we
play, and um some modern techniques and
examples
that um you know, hopefully is helpful
in understanding like now now that
you've kind of got a grasp of the
history like what does it actually look
like today. Um so yeah, thank you all
for listening. Um, again, apologies for
the technical difficulties earlier, but
um,
uh, yeah, hope you guys enjoyed.
Yeah, thanks Muhammad. Um, so yeah, I'm
going to like show some, you know,
specific examples of um, yeah, like
RL training runs which use a sandbox. Um
and yeah also like examine okay so so
like what does modern reinforcement
learning look like? um you know like
there's a lot of we don't like
necessarily know we don't really know
like how the open AI models that have
solved you know all these open
mathematical problems have been trained
but we do know like a lot of about at
least Chinese models Kimmy K2 um GLM and
then also into west the composer too
which is also based on Kim but yeah so
like we do know some things about you
know how the modern an RL is done and
you know one thing that we do know is
that you know it's done in sandboxes um
which means you know every uh you know
agent gets an isolated computer in which
it you know does a certain task um and
then it's graded based on some
verifiable criterion I mean there's also
like more things that come to it and
we're going to see some of them Um but
overall yeah that's that's kind of the
standard right now which is you know
just um roll outs in their sandboxes. Um
and that's also kind of a side effect of
nowadays coding being the biggest uh
biggest application of these models. Um
so yeah um we're gonna see like a
specific training run on quen 38
billion. Um we're just doing some
standard Python things in a terminal
basically and you know we're just going
to like examine what happened during
that run. Um some things might
generalize like big training runs some
might not. Uh but yeah um and yeah for
this example we're going to be using uh
sky RL for like the trainer part and um
harbor for the environments and rollout
part and uh the environment is going to
be daton sandboxes basically uh but I
mean it's a it could be run in any kind
of sandbox um so yeah and it's a
I mean this kind of points to one thing
that is like maybe worth mentioning
which is that you know in RL you
basically have two parts. One is the
part that generates your rollouts um and
the other is the trainer which updates
the weights and you know they nowadays
you know usually you have like different
libraries dealing with each of them and
then you have like some different
sandbox substrate. Um so yeah that
that's uh one kind of distinction worth
keeping in mind. Um so this is one uh
this is kind of the the case study of
reinforcement learning run. It's quent
38 billion
um you know run on eight H100s over four
hours um starting with about 30%
accuracy or rather the the 0.3 reward
but that is basically because this is
the binary reward that that corresponds
to the accuracy and solving these coding
tasks.
um you know four hours over which 1440
rollouts happened um you rather it tried
to solve that many problems of course
some of them repeating
um so yeah we're going to just
hop into this different slide where
we're basically going to see
that training run sped up um sped up
like 60 times here. Um, so here we can
see it GPU utilization which is going to
be a bit jumpy. Um, in some like uh
super optimized uh setups you wouldn't
like have it super jumpy but here there
like some downtime as the sandboxes
start up um and as the episodes wind
down basically. Uh but yeah basically
you can see so this is like going at 60
times. So each second represents like
one second of the training run. Um here
you can see so each step involves eight
tasks four rollouts for each of those
tasks. Some of them fail some of them
succeed. U sandboxes are getting created
all the time. uh in each step 32 of them
then torn down um the reward is like
slowly climbing up um over this time.
You can also see like the breakdown here
of like okay so each individual step in
this training run how much does each of
its like subcomponents take? Um and you
know usually it is in in RL training
runs that like most of the time you
spend on um an on actual roll out so
like the model acting um you know
generating its turns etc. But then you
also have the where like you know doing
the backwards pass which can also be
like kind of a non-trivial part of it.
Um and you also have the the weight
syncing. Uh so after you you've updated
the weights, you want to like the so in
your trainer part, you want your uh roll
out generator parts to get new weights
or other new policy. Um yeah, this is an
example of like a completely synchronous
reinforcement learning run. Um so that
yeah you just do one step you update the
weights you u update the policy or
update more update the weights um and
then you do the next step the future
rollouts with completely new weights
updated um so this is like one of the
things that's done a bit differently in
in the name of like uh efficiency
nowadays um there's like a few
optimizations we are going to see and
that are like used in like these big
training runs such as Gimme K3 and GLM
runs. Um but yeah, this is like wrapping
up slowly. Um this training run I mean
sped up 60 times. Um but yeah, the the
kind of the thing to notice here is yeah
just there's like this whole cycle. Some
of it involves the weight. Some of it is
uh related to sandboxes which spawn for
uh for individual rollouts in each step.
Yeah.
Um so yeah one kind of thing that um you
know I think it's kind of interesting
about reinforcement learning is that you
know in some ways it can be more
interpretable than like pre-training.
um because
usually like the volume of the of data
is smaller and you can just look at the
trajectories and see you know what the
model found that worked um
just you know like kind of analyze them
there's a there's a much smaller amount
of data basically so in this previous
run uh so model went from you know like
let's say 30% success to approximately
60% success um but kind of an
interesting ing thing is just to notice
what it kind of learned. It didn't learn
some new insights about algorithms and
such thingies, but it just learn to
format, you know, what it wrote better.
So, it didn't do like double quoting
inside double quotes when it wrote
things to a Python file to a text file.
Um, it didn't uh, you know, one of the
things that tripped it up. So it
happened in about a quarter of rollouts
at the start was it would output the you
know the literal new line character
rather than actual new line and so so
like that's those are the things that
the model kind of actually learned
during this training run and it kind of
connects to that um you know whole
debate like whether RL actually teaches
the model new things or does it just
like reinforcing things that were
thought to it during pre-training. Um,
and I mean at least in this example, you
know, we we could just say that the
model mostly learn to like deal with the
format of things like that to to um deal
with it with harness uh rather than
learning some like new algorithmic
thingies. uh uh so yeah um in each roll
out you basically only train on the
agent tokens you'll have al also like
dual results etc etc so I mean this is a
bit of a
a bit of a technical thing about on
which tokens to actually train but yeah
let's go into the meat of like okay so
what happened during like some of these
big recent training runs um yeah kic
there's like a lot of a lot of
interesting details in their tech
report. Um, and you know that they do
state exactly that they used 51 million
sandboxes. Um,
uh, they also like used microVMs for it.
Um, and in particular there's like one
one interesting
uh feature of like microVM. So they like
used the pause feature a lot because
Kimmy like tends to think a lot between
turns and so so basically what this
means is that you can like pause the
sandbox between the turns um while it's
doing the thinking so it's not using up
the compute resources. Um so yeah
there's like um
uh like a lot of interesting details.
One of them is like how did they prepare
the model to like be ready for you know
any hardness that could be thrown to at
it like so it works at Kimmy Schmi code
but it also you know works at cloud
codecs etc etc and what they did what
they did was like a a dynamic harness
where they like basically have a config
which turns off and on various like
aspects of harness like system prompts
sub agents, memories, skills, etc. And
like doing that, they kind of like use
this as a data augmentation access. Um,
so they like get
data augmentation. They they they
prepared the model for like all the
current hardnesses, but also like
probably some future ones because it's
um it's trained on many permutations of
features of the harness.
Um yeah that's that's kind of a
interesting contrast with the composer 2
approach because composer 2 which is
cursor's um model they basically like
specifically trained it on the harness
for for cursor. So like like um Kimy's
approach is basically diversity harness
diversity and achieving robustness to
anything you could throw at it. while
the composer to approach from cursor was
like let's get this model really ready
for for cursor. Um so that is kind of a
quite a different approach to to
preparing the model for it agentic work.
Um so yeah um here's like a couple of
other kind of interesting aspects of
Kimik training. Um I mean this is about
how they taught it different reasoning
levels. Um they were basically just you
know for a given reasoning level
give some token budget which is also
like problem dependent. Uh and then also
like just if the model went over the
token budget, they would just um you
know just give it minus one reward. Um
irregard irregardless of where it was
right actually. Um
and yeah, so like the final model
actually comp was composed of nine
reinforcement learning learning runs. um
which are then you know we then on
policy distilled onto the final model.
Um and so so they do did like nine
models. Uh so the matrix one model for
each reasoning level low, high and max
but also they had like general model
like general conversations the agent
agentic model and a coding model. Um so
there was like nine separate
reinforcement learning runs and then all
of them got distilled into the final
model. So I mean they did verifiably did
some distillation. Um we just uh we just
don't know if it was also on some other
models but this like kind of approach of
training expert models and then
distilling them onto your kind of main
model. Um so yeah the on policy
distillation is kind of a technique
that's now nowadays used a lot and it
kind of composes nicely with
reinforcement learning in general. Um so
basically as in this Kim K3 example they
had like you know let's say say some you
know coding expert model and then they
would generate rollouts with their you
know generalist model
um which is not to be confused with the
general um
general model in the previous slide but
just like their final model. they would
generate rollouts with it and they would
score its tokens with the expert model.
Um and that way they would like you know
they would distill all these models um
you know kind of impart part of their
wisdom into the final model. Um and this
is like a pretty versatile technique.
You need to you know you need to access
to the model so you can get its full log
props for for every token. But yeah, if
you do it's um it's pretty powerful for
you know distilling or going from a from
a teacher to a stu student model.
Um and yeah another kind of like
interesting thing nowadays is that yeah
you need like a lot of environments um
and that's like a pretty big industry
nowadays. Um but Kimikry and GM at least
like do share some details about how
they actually make synthetic
environments with their with their
agents. Um
so like there like a lot of variety
there. Um and uh Kimik3 actually has
like this big directed cyclic graph of
like the internet where like they try to
like cover every area with some
synthetic environment. Um and just yeah
the the
kind of the environments is a new form
of data so to say. So so previously
would like try to increase your data set
as much as as you could. Nowadays like
there's a lot decent amount of
pre-training data on the internet but
there's like not that many environments
and the environments are the currently
actually valuable part of the kind of
the data stack and then you know you
want to employ your models into building
better and better environments.
Um
so yeah um
one other thing that's like pretty
prominent with the current models is
like the prevalence of reward hacking
which is basically when a model does
something that kind of on the paper
satisfies your reward satisfy your
verifier but it doesn't like actually
correspond to the actual thing that was
um supposed to be done. So there's like
this very famous illustration of reward
hacking from 2016 from OpenAI from like
a very simplistic game where the model
was you know it was supposed to learn
this game but it just like learned to
spin in a circle and collect these kind
of score packets. Um and yeah so what
one says with LLMs is you know something
like this but just a lot more
sophisticated because you know your kind
of policy is actually
you know an intelligent agent which is
you know actually trying to and you know
now as we know actually um reward
hacking has like kind of become literal
um it has you know has literally become
hacking nowadays um at least in in some
cases. Um so yeah, there's like Kimmy
and GLM at least talk like a lot about
um you know these specific measures that
they took. So for various kind of en
environments they do different
interventions that prevent uh that you
know supposed to prevent or amilarate um
reward hacking and like for example
writing kernels is like one of the
environments in which there's like a lot
of ways to hack. So, um
there's a there's like a lot of effort
needed to expand to make sure that your
reward is actually a real one and then
not a not a kind of a
just a quirk of your verifier so to say.
Um so yeah um what has actually so I
talked a little bit about this before on
that like live rather sped up run um so
where does the you know in a single step
in reinforcement learning where does the
time go and I mean it's mostly uh inter
rollouts because yeah models take a lot
of time to think they possibly execute
actions which take a long time to
execute um and so that that's kind the
part that costs you the most. Um, and in
particular in like the fully synchronous
reinforcement learning, you're
constrained by your longest rollouts
roll out so that you know you're just
waiting on all the episodes to finish so
you can go to your, you know, backwards
pass to your weight syncing part. Um and
yeah so so you just you're waiting
possibly a long time for a single roll
out to finish. Um and that's actually
you know one thing that's yeah not much
time so I'm going to speed through a bit
through a couple of these slides but
basically um you know you can just try
to generate as many rollouts as you can
not wait for some specific ones to
finish and just wait for a certain
number of them to finish
and then immediately you know update
your policy update your weights. Um so
that's the asynchronous reinforcement
learning and it's you know quite popular
nowadays for maximizing throughput. Um
but yeah there like some you know you
get you know rollouts generated by stale
policy and you know that's kind of it
you know both breaks some of the
like the theoretical assumptions of uh
you know reinforcement learning
algorithms but also it you know just
makes the whole thing more unstable and
reinforcement learning is like already
kind of notoriously unstable. Um so yeah
you you you kind of do that as a sort of
a trick and Kim Kitri actually did like
something between synchronous and
asynchronous reinforcement learning
which is that you know they collected
like a certain amount of rollouts they
would pause but they would like then
pause the rollouts for the next um
for the next weight sync. So, so they
would like uh it's a bit of a less
extreme version of the asynchronous
reinforcement learning. Um fully
asynchronous, yeah, the policy moves on
and it just um
you get a lot of staleness of it which
can hurt you in some non-trivial ways
during the training process. Um
yeah, so that's more or less it. So
we've seen that yeah the the kind of
like the API of modern reinforcement
learning is pretty standardized now. You
have you know your trainer your rollout
generator and you have you know
somewhere where your sandboxes are run.
Um and yeah that's what we've seen in
the tunnel like a lot of demand for
sandboxes specifically in reposting.
So yeah that's it. There's like a repo
which you can find if you want to um
like look at the code that generated
some of these things in the in the
presentation.
Um
and that's it. Thank you all.
All right. Thank you, Daytona. We have
lunchtime now uh outside in Lower Sprawl
Plaza. There'll be lunch and at the
first floor we have our posters and and
sponsors. So, we'll be back at 1:30. So,
enjoy lunch. Thank you.